Here is the primary chart:
Brent crude on the daily
timeframe. The July tenth close
was seventy-five twenty-two. The July
thirteenth close was eighty-three thirty-one.
Tuesday opened at eighty-four, reached
eighty-seven fifty-five, and closed at
eighty-five fifteen. That sequence says
the market carried the weekend
repricing forward instead of immediately
erasing it. But notice the
difference between a premium and
a panic. The close did
not hold the session high.
Buyers paid more for the
barrel, while the chart still
rejected the upper edge of
the day. The clean decision
area is now eighty-three to
eighty-four underneath and eighty-seven fifty-five
to eighty-eight overhead. Holding the
lower area keeps the geopolitical
premium intact. A completed daily
close above the upper area