Start with what is actually
verified. The International Maritime Organization
said several ships transiting the
Strait of Hormuz were attacked
over the two days before
its July eighth statement. It
did not identify the attackers,
and neither will we. On
July thirteenth, the I M
O Council condemned attacks on
civilian commercial ships in and
around the Strait and called
for work toward a coordinated,
sustainable return to unhindered navigation.
That wording matters. It establishes
a volatile shipping environment and
a policy goal. It does
not establish that the Strait
is fully closed, fully open,
or normalized. Then on July
fourteenth, the United States Treasury
said a new sanctions action
covered more than fifty individuals,
entities, and vessels in a