Here is the map, not
a prediction. The base case
is Brent holding roughly eighty-three
to eighty-eight, X L E
holding fifty-six twenty-nine, and V
I X staying below seventeen
fifty-six. That combination says the
market is charging an energy-specific
premium without broad contagion. Escalation
requires a verified new disruption
or enforcement development plus a
completed Brent close above eighty-seven
fifty-five. Better confirmation would be
X L E above fifty-seven
twenty-two. A ten-year yield above
four point six three-six or
V I X above seventeen
fifty-six would confirm that the
shock is spreading beyond energy.
De-escalation requires an official navigation
improvement plus Brent losing the
eighty-three to eighty-four area and
X L E losing fifty-six
twenty-nine. A headline without the
chart is incomplete. A chart
break without a verified event
can be a different catalyst.
The strongest signal is agreement