Oil is carrying a war
premium, but the rest of
the market is refusing to
panic. Brent finished Tuesday at
eighty-five fifteen after trading as
high as eighty-seven fifty-five. Energy
stocks confirmed the move. Yet
the volatility index closed Monday
at sixteen fifty, not even
above its seventeen fifty-six session
high, while the S and
P and Nasdaq recovered on
Tuesday. That split is the
story. The market sees real
shipping risk around the Strait
of Hormuz, but it has
not promoted that risk into
a synchronized portfolio crisis. Today
we separate the verified event
from the headline noise, read
the levels straight from TradingView,
and build a scenario map
for what would confirm escalation,