Now test the broad market.
The S and P five
hundred closed July tenth at
seventy-five seventy-five thirty-nine. It dropped
to a Monday low of
seventy-five oh-six forty-one and closed
that session at seventy-five fifteen
thirty-four. On Tuesday it recovered
to seventy-five forty-three fifty-nine. The
Nasdaq tells the same story.
It closed July tenth at
twenty-six thousand two hundred eighty-one
sixty-one, finished Monday at twenty-five
thousand eight hundred seventy-three eighteen
after a low of twenty-five
thousand eight hundred twenty-two oh-nine,
then recovered Tuesday to twenty-six
thousand one hundred seven oh-one.
Those are not untouched charts,
but they are not synchronized
panic charts either. Broad equity
confirmation would require the S
and P to lose the
seventy-five oh-six to seventy-five fifteen