Why can a shipping event
matter so much? The mechanism
runs through transit risk, freight,
insurance, and the reliability of
oil flows. The Energy Information
Administration estimated total Hormuz oil
flows at twenty point seven
million barrels per day in
the fourth quarter of last
year and fourteen point six
million barrels per day in
the first quarter of this
year. Those are historical estimates,
not current traffic counts. The
E I A also warns
that automatic-identification data for Hormuz
have been especially unreliable since
the end of February and
that this year's estimates are
revised frequently. So we will
not pretend to know the
current number of ships or
barrels moving through the Strait.
What we can say is
that renewed transit danger and
sanctions enforcement can increase perceived