This war did not start
this week. U.S. Central Command
says Operation Epic Fury began
on February twenty-eighth, and this
is its own strike footage
from March first. The bombs
are real. The damage is
real. The human cost is
real. The International Maritime Organization's
current incident table counts fifty-six
maritime incidents and eighteen seafarer
deaths as of July fifteenth.
Two more ships were damaged
off Oman on Tuesday. One
was abandoned. People were killed
and injured. This is not
headline theater. This is a
live shipping risk. But the
market does not price every
explosion the same. It prices
the bottleneck. The Strait of
Hormuz is the pressure point
between Gulf exports and open
water. When trust in that
route falls, the first bill
shows up in the barrel.