Now test the broad market.
The S and P five
hundred fell to seventy-five oh-six
on Monday, then recovered to
seventy-five forty-three on Tuesday. It
took a hit. It did
not break into disorder. That
matters because a true risk-off
regime should not need excuses
from the index. V I
X makes the split even
clearer. It closed Monday at
sixteen fifty after trading as
high as seventeen fifty-six. Early
today it was near sixteen
sixteen. If fear were spreading
across the whole market, volatility
should be expanding with oil.
Instead, it is sitting near
the lower end of the
recent range. The ten-year yield
is near four point five
seven, below Tuesday's four point
five eight seven close and
below Monday's four point six
two four close. That does
not mean inflation risk disappeared.
It means the rates market
is not buying a fresh
breakout yet. Oil is shouting.
Bonds are listening, but they
are not running. If this
were broad panic, the S
and P, V I X,
and the ten-year would be
yelling with the barrel. They
are not. So I am
not using the word crisis
for the portfolio regime. The
war is a crisis for
people in it. The market
regime, for now, is selective
repricing.