Look at the map. Iran
sits on the north side
of the Strait. Oman sits
on the south. Gulf ports
and export infrastructure sit behind
a narrow exit into the
Gulf of Oman. The geography
does not predict an attack.
It explains why a shipping
incident in this corridor can
reach a portfolio faster than
an incident far from a
trade route. The I M
O Council is focused on
the established traffic separation scheme
and a sustainable return to
unhindered navigation. In trader language,
the route still exists, but
the cost of trusting it
has gone up. Markets can
price that loss of trust
before a formal closure ever
appears. This is where our
Godseye view earns the cut.
Not as a spinning globe.
As a pressure map. The
route, the surrounding coast, and
the energy infrastructure belong in
one frame because they explain
the mechanism. If the map
does not teach the trade,
it does not make the
edit. I am not going
to paint fake ship traffic
onto the water. A I
S coverage can be incomplete,
and the feed has no
guaranteed Gulf receiver coverage. An
empty patch on a screen
does not mean an empty
sea. The map owns geography.
The incident table owns the
event record. The charts own
the market reaction.