Here is the base case.
Brent holds between roughly eighty-three
and eighty-eight. X L E
stays above fifty-six twenty-nine. V
I X stays below seventeen
fifty-six. That is a bottleneck
premium with limited contagion. Energy
gets paid. The broad market
keeps trading its own earnings
and growth story. Escalation needs
more than another frightening clip.
I want a new shipping
incident or policy shock, a
completed Brent close above eighty-seven
fifty-five to eighty-eight, and at
least one second gauge. X
L E above fifty-seven twenty-two
says producers agree. V I
X above seventeen fifty-six says
fear is spreading. If oil
spikes but X L E
and V I X refuse,
I treat the move as
narrow until the chain proves
otherwise. That is not complacency.
It is position discipline. One
market can be right about
one risk without every asset
joining the same trade. An
unwind also needs two pieces.
I want an official improvement
in navigation, then Brent below
eighty-three to eighty-four and X
L E below fifty-six twenty-nine.