This morning's Producer Price Index
adds a useful twist. Final
demand prices fell zero point
three percent in June. Goods
prices fell one point four
percent. Energy prices fell six
point four percent. Services rose
zero point two percent. The
headline says producer inflation cooled
before the latest jump in
oil. But June P P
I is the rear-view mirror.
Today's Brent chart is the
windshield. The report captures the
old energy decline. The market
is now deciding whether July's
war premium reverses part of
that relief. Mixing those two
time periods is how a
clean number turns into a
bad trade. The P P
I measure that strips out
food, energy, and trade services
rose zero point one percent
in June and five point
one percent over the year.